A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1001
ca. 25,000 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
The papers in MSS 1001 were given to the University of Virginia Special Collections Department by Mrs. Edwin A. Alderman, on November 7, 1940. Over the years, various other accessions have been interfiled into these papers; these MSS numbers include: MSS 801; MSS 827 (Gift from Joseph L. Vaughan, May 3, 1940); MSS 1206 (Gift from Joseph L. Vaughan, August 12, 1940); MSS 1315; MSS 1383; MSS 1551 (Gift from the University of Virginia President's Office, November 6, 1942); MSS 1736; MSS 2056 (Transfer from the Preparations Division, December 14, 1944); MSS 2636 (Transfer from the University of Virginia President's Office, March 4, 8, 1947); MSS 2649-a; MSS 2739; MSS 3087 (Loaned by Mrs. Wayne M. Rule, January 10, 1949, until a photostatic copy was made, and then the original was returned on January 13, 1949); MSS 3558 (Gift from Allie Gregory, September 20, 1950); MSS 3571 (Gift from Allie Gregory, October 10, 1950); MSS 5438; MSS 6752 (Transfer from the University of Virginia President's Office, March 20, 1962); and MSS 7606 (Gift of Thomas Fullbright, June 23, 1964).
Biographical Information
Edwin Anderson Alderman (1861-1931) served as the President of three universities. The University of Virginia's Alderman Library is named after him, as is Edwin A. Alderman Elementary School in Wilmington.
Alderman graduated from the University of North Carolina in 1882. He became a schoolteacher in Goldsboro, North Carolina, and then superintendent of the school district there.
In 1891, Alderman and Charles Duncan McIver successfully pressed the North Carolina Legislature to establish the Normal and Industrial School for Women, now known as the University of North Carolina at Greensboro. Alderman taught there until 1893, when he became a professor at the University of North Carolina; he was named president of that institution in 1896. He moved on to take the same position at Tulane University in 1900, before moving again to the University of Virginia in 1904. There he stayed for 27 years, until his death in 1931 from a stroke in Connellsville, Pennsylvania, while en route to deliver a speech in Illinois. He is buried at the University of Virginia Cemetery.
Alderman was a noted public speaker, and won fame for his memorial address for Woodrow Wilson, delivered to a joint session of Congress on December 15, 1924.
In 1904, the Board of Visitors of the University of Virginia invited Alderman, then president of Tulane University, to become the first president of the University of Virginia. Since its founding in 1819, Mr. Jefferson's University had been governed by its Board of Visitors, but increasing discord between Visitors and the faculty, as well as the rising administrative burden of dealing with expanding academic departments and burgeoning student enrollments, led to the decision to move forward with the creation of the office of the president.
Alderman was not the first choice for the new office. After considering other candidates, including Virginia Law graduate Woodrow Wilson, the Board of Visitors had first invited its former member George W. Miles, a colonel who had served on the staff of Virginia Governor James Hoge Tyler. The faculty opposed Miles' nomination and he was forced to withdraw. Other candidates were proposed, including Francis Preston Venable (who had succeeded Alderman as president of the University of North Carolina), but Alderman was unanimously chosen as the consensus candidate on June 14, 1904. He began to serve in the fall of 1904 but was not formally inaugurated until April 13, 1905 (Thomas Jefferson's birthday, which was then as now celebrated as Founder's Day).
The University changed in several significant ways under Alderman's guidance. First, he focused new attention on matters of public concern, creating departments of geology and forestry, adding significantly to the University Hospital to support new sickbeds and public health research, created the Curry School of Education, established the extension and summer school programs, and created the first school of finance and commerce at the school. He then restructured existing programs, separating the former "academic department" into the College of Arts and Sciences and Graduate School of Arts and Sciences, in accordance with a growing move to standardize college educations by the Association of American Universities. The enrollment of the school greatly increased under his administration, as well, going from 500 regular session students in 1904 to 2,200 in 1929.
Alderman also laid the financial groundwork for the University's future, during the first years of his presidency establishing its first endowment fund and leading the fundraising of almost $700,000 to meet a $500,000 challenge grant from Andrew Carnegie. By the end of his presidency the endowment would increase to $10 million.
He spent two-thirds of his long term at the University of Virginia physically disabled after a bad bout with tuberculosis.
Information taken from Wikipedia article: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edwin_Alderman
Scope and Content
The papers consist of personal and official correspondence, drafts of speeches, scrapbooks, photographs, clippings, memorabilia, and other papers, ca. 1863-1959, ca. 25,000 items (29 Hollinger boxes, 2 card file boxes and 5 Oversize boxes, ca. 21.5 linear feet). The correspondence and other papers chiefly relate to Alderman's work at the University of Virginia, but also includes his education and early associations; his work in the public schools and at the Woman's College at Greensboro, North Carolina; his presidency of the University of North Carolina, and Tulane University; his activities with the Southern Education Board, the Association of American Universities, and other organizations. Includes drafts of most of his noted orations; several bibliographies of his writings, correspondence, and scrapbooks kept by his wife, Bessie Green Hearn Alderman.
Correspondents and persons mentioned include Charles Francis Adams, Henry Adams, Felix Adler, James Rowland Angell, Nancy Astor, Charles B. Aycock, Karl Bitter, Nicholas Murray Butler, Richard E. Byrd, Grover Cleveland, Calvin Coolidge, J.L.M. Curry, Frank B. Dancy, Josephus Daniels, Westmoreland Davis, Charles W. Eliot, Alfred William Erickson, John H. Finley, Thomas Staples Fuller, Williamson Whitehead Fuller, and Carter Glass. Also, Warren G. Harding, Herbert Hoover, William Dean Howells, and Jean Jusserand, Franklin K. Lane, [Philip Henry Kerr] the Marquis of Lothian, Hamilton W. Mabie, Charles D. McIver, A. T. Mahan, John S. Mosby, Edward P. Moses, M.C.S. Noble, Thomas Nelson Page, Walter Hines Page, George F. Peabody, John J. Raskob, Franklin D. Roosevelt, George Bernard Shaw, William Howard Taft, Amélie Rives Troubetzkoy, Oswald Garrison Villard, Booker T. Washington, Joseph R. Wilson, and Woodrow Wilson.
Speeches and addresses by Alderman form a large part of the collection and are in various stages of construction from notes, manuscripts, and typescripts, to a printed version, often printed in whole or in part in The Alumni Bulletin or as a separate publication. Whenever possible, all versions of the same speech can be found together in a single folder under the date of the original speech even though the published version came later.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence (Boxes 1-11), Subseries A arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent and Subseries B: Topical Correspondence. Series II: Topical Files (Boxes 12-17); Series III: Speeches, Articles, and Addresses (Boxes 18-29) by Edwin A. Alderman arranged chronologically by the date originally delivered or published if known. Many of his speeches delivered after he became President of the University of Virginia can be found in printed form in the University of Virginia Alumni Bulletin (LH1.V6 A4) either in the issue current with the speech or the next issue following his speech and in several volumes of the Rare Book bound pamphlet series (F221, volumes: 23-26 and 41-47). Many items appear to have been previously removed from a scrapbook and have vestiges of glue and paper remaining on them. Series IV: Scrapbooks and Note cards (Boxes 29-31, and Alderman Oversize Boxes 1- 5).
Contents List
- Series I: Correspondence
  - 1903-1927 Correspondence: A, including Lyman Abbott (1835-1922), editor of The Outlook; Felix Adler (1851-1933); E[dward] P[orter] Alexander (1835-1910), writes concerning the Panama versus the Nicaragua canal route controversy (January 9, 1904) and his war memoirs (August 29, 1907); Alfred G. Alderman; Dorothy Alderman; James Harris Alderman; Superintendent J.T. Alderman; A.T. Allen, Superintendent of Public Instruction; American Association of University Professors; Archibald Anderson; Harry A. Anderson; Robert C. Angell; James Rowland Angell (1869-1949), President of the Carnegie Foundation, Alderman writes explaining why he requested a donation towards the University of Virginia Centennial endowment drive (April 21 and 28, 1921); Charles Brantley Aycock (1859-1912), Governor of North Carolina, concerning his gubernatorial address (February 12, 1901); and Alderman to Frank Aydelotte, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, concerning Alderman's attempt to bring about closer academic relations between the United States and England (December 12, 1918) (Box-folder 1:1)
  - 1903-1913, 1925-1928 Correspondence: Bessie Green Hearn Alderman from Edwin A. Alderman, writes about his trip out West to San Francisco (March 24, April 1906), the gift from Patrick Calhoun of $50,000 for the University of Virginia while on his trip (March 30, 1906), and the bad snowstorm at Denver, Colorado (April 5, 1906); postcards and letters from England and Scotland tell details of his visit, especially to Oxford (June 16-28, 1908); reports on his health and Christmas while at Saranac Lake, New York (Christmas Day, 1912 and December 28, 1912); other letters from Saranac also describe his progress and activities (1912-1913); his impression of Governor Al Smith at Albany, New York (September 14, 1928); and the only item from 1903 is an empty envelope (Box-folder 1:2)
  - 1932-1935 Correspondence: Bessie Green Hearn Alderman from Edward Mandell House, chiefly about finding someone to write Alderman's biography, settling upon Dumas Malone as their choice (Box-folder 1:3)
  - 1931-1942 Correspondence: Bessie Green Hearn Alderman from Miscellaneous correspondents, chiefly expressing their sympathy upon the death of Edwin A. Alderman or thanking Mrs. Alderman for sending a copy of Finley's tribute to Alderman or one of Alderman's personal books. Correspondents include: George Gordon Battle (May 5, 1932); Hugh Black (March 2, 1932); Elizabeth Marion Bryce, chiefly social notes but also includes a mention of the tragedy of the Titanic (April 20, 1912); Harry F. Byrd, Sr. (March 17, 1933 and July 23, 1935); Marie A. Byrd possibly writing about her husband, Richard Evelyn Byrd, while he was in Antarctica (August 23, [1934?]); Richard Evelyn Byrd (July 26, 1939); Edmund S. Campbell concerning four Heppelwhite chairs from the Tiffany Collection (December 19, 1932); William Perrin Carmichael [1931?]; Harry Clemons acknowledging gifts from Bessie Alderman to the Library (July 29, 30, 1935; plus one letter from her about some photographs, March 18, 1941); Luella B. Cook, seeking permission to quote from one of Alderman's speeches (June & July 1932); Governor Colgate W. Darden, Jr. (January 22, 1942); James Hardy Dillard (April 30, 1931; April 28, 1932); [Mrs. Richard L. Dobie] (June 22); William E. Dodd (June 13, 1933); and E. Griffith Dodson (May 13, 1941). (Box-folder 1:4)
    Other correspondents include: John Huston Finley (May 8, 1932); Martha Finley (December 2, 1932); Douglas Southall Freeman (October 15, 1934); F.L. Fuller, Jr. (May 4, 1932); Dr. William V.P. Garretson (April 25, 1932); Carter Glass (June 11, 1937); Marian Diane Graham (September 5, 1932); Hollins College Corporation concerning Alderman's connection with Hollins (August 8, 1932); Lou Henry Hoover, the White House (May 5, 1931, January 13, 1933); Cordell Hull (May 17, 1940); James T. White & Company concerning Alderman's entry in the National Cyclopedia of American Biography (July 13, 1932); and [Philip Henry Kerr], 11 th marquis of Lothian (September 5, 1939). Other correspondents include: Jim McConnell on service with the Lafayette Escadrille in France which mentions his articles on his work as an ambulance driver and aviator, his smash up which hurt his back, his convalescence in Paris, sleeping on the ground and preparing for the Somme, and his shame that the United States is neutral in the war (October 30, 1916); J.C. Metcalf [1932?]; Robert Watton Moore (September 28, 1933; May 24, 1937); Dr. Rosalie Slaughter Morton concerning an awarded diploma and a decoration that was never sent to Alderman from Yugoslavia (January 30 and April 6, 1932); Grace Newcomb (April 29, 1932); John Lloyd Newcomb thanking her for gifts to the University (August 25 and October 31, 1932; October 10, 1933; July 31 and August 16, 1935); Marcus Cicero Stephens Noble sending a copy of his eulogy for Alderman at Chapel Hill (October 25, 1932); J.M. Page concerning his own health (May 6, 1932); George Foster Peabody (May 31, 1931); John Garland Pollard (May 7, 1932); Franklin D. Roosevelt, originals transferred to the Vault (September 8, 1933; October 26, 1936); Francis B. Sayre (January 23, 1933); Frederic William Scott (April 19, 1932); Charles Alphonso Smith (May 5, 1931); Amelie Rives Troubetzkoy (May 25, 1931); Virgilia Whitehead (May 1, 1932); and the University of North Carolina concerning a tablet to honor Alderman and to be placed in their Memorial Hall (April 15, 25, 27, and May 9, 1932)
  - 1910-1914 Correspondence: Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (1905- ), chiefly letters from his father, Edwin A. Alderman, Sr., when he was a child and his father was away recuperating at Saranac Lake, New York. There is one letter from Edwin, Jr. about John Burns to Mr. [Woods?] Price (September 24, 1914), who returned it to Mrs. Alderman on September 13, 1922, with his own letter on the back of Edwin's letter, mentioning the death of John Burns of Australia and his service in World War I in Gallipoli and France (Box-folder 1:5)
  - 1920-1922 Correspondence: Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (1905- ), chiefly letters from his family and teachers concerning his education while away at Episcopal High School, Alexandria, Virginia (Box-folder 1:6)
  - 1922-1924 Correspondence: Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (1905- ), chiefly letters from his family and teachers concerning his education while away at Haverford School, Haverford, Pennsylvania, and a two items from attending the University of Virginia (Box-folder 1:7)
  - 1929 Correspondence: Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (1905- ), letters from February and March chiefly those of Alderman, Sr. on his son's behalf while he was looking for a job in the New York publishing industry, where he eventually became employed by Harcourt, Brace and Company in early March; discusses prohibition and drinking among college students (April 14, 1929; October 27, 1929); disagreement over the marriage plans of Edwin Alderman, Jr. and Anne Polk Cucullu (July); and many discussion about finances and employment (August - December) (Box-folder 1:8)
  - 1930-1932 Correspondence: Edwin A. Alderman, Jr. (1905- ), explains his change in jobs (April 30, 1930); the illness of Anne and her absence from New York to recover (September 30, 1930); several of Edwin's book reviews have been published in the [New York] Times [October 4 & 18, 1930]; November 4, 1930; and several letters following); and his regret at the passing of The Evening World (March 2, 1931) (Box-folder 1:9)
  - 1930-1931 Correspondence: American Academy of Arts and Letters (Box-folder 1:10)
  - [1912-1913?]-1922 Correspondence: Nancy Witcher (Langhorne) Astor (1879-1964), mentions Woodrow Wilson's campaign for President ([1912-1913?]); and Alderman seeking a donation towards the University of Virginia Centennial endowment drive (April 13, 1921) (Box-folder 1:11)
  - 1891-1931 Correspondence: B, including Irving Bacheller (1859-1950); Senator J[oseph] W. Bailey, Texas; William Henry Baldwin, Jr. (1863-1905), one letter responds to news from Alderman of his upcoming marriage to Bessie Hearn (October 30, 1903); Stringfellow Barr concerning his plans for his doctorate (1922-1923); P.B. Barringer to Alderman, mentions that one of the Board of Visitors, Colonel Miles, is interested in the presidency of the University of Virginia, but the faculty are not supporting him (March 11, 1903); Alderman to Dr. P.B. Barringer, expresses his surprise at being chosen president of the University of Virginia and asks Barringer to "talk straight" to him when he comes to visit (photostatic copy, June 21, 1904); and Alderman to Dr. P.B. Barringer, writes a six page letter about the work of the Committee on the courses of instruction in Engineering offered at the University of Virginia, the Virginia Military Institute, and the Virginia Polytechnic Institute, which committee was formed at the request of the Educational Commission of Virginia (June 2, 1911); Alderman to George Gordon Battle about Woodrow Wilson's nomination (July 8, 1912) and Battle to Alderman about missing him at the dinner with Governor Wilson (December 23, 1912); Alderman to Dr. Henry W. Battle, apparently addressing Battle's concern over the religious instruction of University of Virginia students and providing him with the number of students who are church members (November 10, 1921); Kemp Plummer Battle, Sr. (1831-1919), President of the University of North Carolina (1831-1919), writes concerning the need for the states to do more to support their own educational institutions (February 18, 1891); and R.H. Battle (June 15, 1900). (Box-folder 1:12)
    Alderman to E.L. Bemiss about what the University of Virginia has said in regard to service in the military as opposed to remaining in school (May 22, 1917); Christie Benet; John K. Berry; H.E. Bierly, Southern Educational Association; Hugh S. Bird; Karl Bitter writes about doing a replica of his statue of Thomas Jefferson for the University (November 11, 1913); John J. Blair concerning Alderman's marriage to Bessie Hearn [1903]; Alderman to W.A. Blair, regretfully refusing the presidency of the George Peabody College for Teachers (June 11, 1910); N.C. Blanchard; Edward W. Bok; Representative Sydney J. Bowie about Alderman's marriage to Bessie Hearn (January 25, 1904); Leroy Stafford Boyd urging Alderman to run for the President of the United States (November 1, 1924); Alderman to Gamaliel Bradford, acknowledging his gift of The Quick and the Dead (March 16, 1931); R.P. Bridgers; Abraham Brittin writes about Woodrow Wilson's legacy (March 1, 1924); Adele Brittin; John Graham Brooks (1846-1938); Marelle Davis Brooks; John Stewart Bryan referring to the Loving Cup presented to Alderman by the Faculty (June 22, 1910), Alderman's illness and stay at Saranac Lake, New York (March 29, 1913); William Jennings Bryan (1860-1925) asking if he could speak at the University of Virginia about Thomas Jefferson (March 25, 1907) and if Alderman would send a list of dates when he could speak for Bryan who was running for President (telegram, October 8, 1908); Lady Winifred Burghclere (1864-1933) sends a gift, Thirty Nine Steps, to Alderman (March 31 and April 27, 1925); Sir George Geoffrey Gilbert Butler; Marie Madeira Butler; a pass to the House of Lords, signed by T.D. Butler; and [Wallace] Buttrick
  - 1901-1902 Correspondence: Page M. Baker, editor of the Times-Democrat, New Orleans, requests a statement of Alderman's views on education in the South following his speech at the meeting of southern educators at the Waldorf [Astoria] (November 10, 1901); and Alderman asks Baker to publicize the upcoming speech by Booker T. Washington [in New Orleans?] to be delivered to the leaders of Negro education on Friday night, and which Alderman is to introduce (October 30, 1902) (Box-folder 2:1)
  - 1915-1929 Correspondence: Poultney Bigelow (1855-1954), two personal letters discussing Bigelow's public speaking engagements (June 22, 1915 and January 16, 1917); and a third one which asks if the Aldermans would take the Kaiser's grandson, Prince Louis Ferdinand of Prussia, as a guest if he could come in April (March 20, 1929) (Box-folder 2:2)
  - 1908 Correspondence: Robert Somers Brookings (1850-1932) concerning an offer of the Chancellorship of Washington University, St. Louis, Missouri, to Alderman (Box-folder 2:3)
  - 1920-1923 Correspondence: Philip Alexander Bruce writes concerning his work on the History of the University of Virginia (June 8 and December 22, 1920; June 16, 21 and 23, December 9, 1922) (Box-folder 2:4)
  - 1898-1913 Correspondence: British Ambassador James Bryce, chiefly notes about visits and Alderman's illness (Box-folder 2:5)
  - 1901-1925 Correspondence: Nicholas Murray Butler (1862-1947), President of Colombia University, chiefly personal notes but also writes about Professor S.A. Mitchell (February 10, 1913); and Alderman's speech before Congress about Woodrow Wilson (December 16, 1924; January 2, 1925) (Box-folder 2:6)
  - 1903-1923 Correspondence: Dr. Wallace Buttrick (1853-1926), Secretary of the General Education Board, includes three carbons of letters from Alderman concerning the current condition and needs of the University of Virginia and an application for funds from the General Education Board to help supply some of them (November 15, December 7, 1905 and January 11 and 13, 1906) and two carbons from Alderman concerning the centennial of the University and its opportunity to raise an endowment of three million dollars (February 1921) (Box-folder 2:7)
  - 1924-1925 Correspondence: Harry Flood Byrd, Sr. (1887-1965), complimenting Alderman on his eulogy of Woodrow Wilson (December 19, 1924) and Alderman requesting his support for educational needs in Virginia (December 27, 1924 and December 18, 1925) (Box-folder 2:8)
  - 1903-1927 Correspondence: C, including: C & O Railroad concerning the Fourteenth Street Bridge, [Charlottesville] (March 9, 1927); Henry S. Canby; W.A. Candler; Alderman to W.E. Carson, requesting that the headquarters of the Forestry Department remain permanently at the University of Virginia (April 18, 1927); H.H[albrand?] Carter; Alderman to John Armstrong Chaloner concerning his gifts of photographs and a bust of Napoleon to the Library (April 30. 1917); D.H. Chamberlain; Mary L. Cheney (January 26, [1903]); Joseph H. Choate concerning the General Arbitration Treaties of 1911-1912 (October 23, 1911); W.A. Clark; Frank Clover; John B. Cobb; Mary C. Love Collins, Chi Omega; Alice T. Connally concerning his upcoming marriage to Bessie Hearn and the deposition of J.M.L. Curry's collection of pamphlets and volumes (November 18, 1903); Charles R. Crane; and Alderman to Elizabeth Cutting, offering an article to the North American Review (March 19, 1923) (Box-folder 2:9)